Guide to the Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas Papers,
1915-1987
Kun, Agnes
4 linear ft. (5 archival document boxes and 1 flat box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0535
9189851
The papers comprise the correspondence of Agnes Kun (1915-1990), translator, and Antal Hidas (1899-1980), Hungarian poet, with prominent Russian poets and writers; Antal Hidas's memoirs; and manuscripts of translations from Hungarian and original poetry by famous Russian authors.
History
Agnes Kun (January 21, 1915-October 19, 1990), translator and editor, daughter of Bela Kun, wife of Hungarian poet Antal Hidas (12.18.1899-01.22.1980), who in the 1920s immigrated to the Soviet Union. Both Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas went through the Gulag. Kun and Hidas became the main Soviet experts on Hungarian literature. It was under their leadership that many collections of Hungarian poetry were translated and published in the USSR in the 1950s. They returned to Hungary in 1959.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of significant correspondence with prominent Russian poets and writers and manuscripts of translations from Hungarian and original poetry by famous Russian authors. Among authors whose letters and manuscripts are represented in the collection are: Margarita Aliger, Lili Brik, Kornei Chukovskii, Aleksandr Fadeev, Vera Inber, Lev Kopelev, Leonid Martynov, Boris Pasternak, Boris Polevoi, David Samoilov, Boris Slutskii, Nikolai Tikhonov, Nikolai Zabolotskii, and many others. Oversize materials stored in BAR Flat Box #5.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in four series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1941-1982, undated
Series II: Writings, 1940-1987, undated
Subseries II.1: Antal Hidas's Writings, 1943-1968, undated
Subseries II.2: Writings by Others, 1940-1987, undated
Series III: Printed Materials, 1917, 1940, undated
Series IV: Third Parties Materials, 1915-1947
Subjects
Abašiże, Grigol, 1914-1994; Aliger, Margarita, 1915-1992; Andronikov, Iraklii, 1908-1990; Bazhan, Mykola Platonovych, 1904-1983; Bek, Aleksandr, 1903-1972; Brik, Lili IUr'evna; Budennyi, S. M. (Semen Mikhailovich), 1883-1973; Chukovskii, Kornei, 1882-1969; Chukovskii, Nikolai; Fadeev, Aleksandr, 1901-1956; Fedin, Konstantin, 1892-1977; Hidas, Antal, 1899-; Inber, Vera; Isakovskii, M. (Mikhail), 1900-1973; Kazakevich, Ėmmanuil, 1913-1962; Kedrin, Dmitrii, 1907-1945; Kirsanov, Semen, 1906-1972; Knipovich, E. (Evgeniia); Kopelev, Lev, 1912-1997; Kun, Agnes; Larina, Anna; Levik, Vil'gel'm; Marshak, S. (Samuil), 1887-1964; Martynov, Leonid, 1905-1980; Morits, IUnna, 1937-; Orlova, R. D. (Raisa Davydovna); Papernyi, Z. (Zinovii), 1919-1996; Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich, 1890-1960; Pervomaiskyi, Leonid Solomonovych, 1908-1973; Petrovykh, Mariia, 1908-1979; Polevoi, Boris Nikolaevich; Prokof'ev, Aleksandr Andreevich, 1900-1971; Rozhdestvenskii, Robert, 1932-; Rozhdestvenskii, Vsevolod, 1895-1977; Rozov, Viktor, 1913-2004; Samoilov, D. (David); Slutskii, Boris, 1919-1986; Stel'makh, Mykhailo Panasovych; Surkov, A. A. (Aleksei Aleksandrovich), 1899-1983; Tikhonov, Nikolai Semenovich, 1896-1979; Turkov, Andrei Mikhailovich; Venclova, Antanas, 1906-1971; Voznesenskii, Andrei, 1933-2010; Zharov, Aleksandr, 1904-; Hidas, Antal, 1899-; Hungarian literature.; Literature--Translations into Russian; Russian literature--20th century; Correspondence; Manuscripts; Memoirs; Translations (Documents)
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Purchase 1994
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1941-1982, undated
  The series consists mainly of letters to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas from prominent Russian authors.
  - Abashidze, Grigol, to Antal Hidas, Tbilisi, 1951, (1 telegram) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aliger, Margarita, to Agnes Kun, Moscow, 1966, 1982, (2 autograph letters signed) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Andronikov, Iraklii, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, 1947, 1964, (1 autograph letter signed, 1 typed letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bazhan, Mykola and Nina, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1974, 1978, undated, (3 autograph letters signed, 14 autograph postcards signed) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bek, Aleksandr, to Agnes Kun, December 14, 1960, (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Belkin, A., to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1961-1969, undated (, 3 autograph letters signed, 4 autograph cards signed) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Borisov, Ivan, to Iren Kun, pos. Shemakhinskii, 1964, (see Series II: Writings--Subseries II.2: Writings by Others--Borisov (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Brik, Lili, to Agnes Kun, Moscow, 1965, (2 autograph letters signed, 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chukovskaia, Marina, (see Chukovskii, Nikolai)
  - Chukovskii, Kornei, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, 1959, 1961, 1963, (2 autograph letters signed, 2 autograph postcards signed) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chukovskii, Nikolai and Marina, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1953-1973, (40 autograph letters signed, 1 typed letter signed, 19 autograph postcards signed, 2 telegrams) (Box 1, Folder 9 to 12)
  - Fadeev, Aleksandr, to various persons, 1941-1944, undated, (2 autograph notes signed, 1 typed letter signed, 1 photocopy of a typed note, 2 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fedin, Konstantin, to Antal Hidas, 1951, 1960, (2 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph postcard signed, 1 envelope) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Inber, Vera, to Agnes Kun, Leningrad, April 2, 1949, (1 autograph letter signed, including manuscript of poetry translations) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Isakovskii, Mikhail, to Agnes Kun, April 20, 1950, (1 typed letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ishov, Mikhail Mikhailovich, to Antal Hidas, Leningrad, undated, (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kazakevich, Ėmmanuil, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, October 1, 1960, (1 typed letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Knipovich, Evgeniia:
    - Letters to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1956-1978, undated, (37 autograph letters signed, 15 autograph postcards signed) (Box 1, Folder 19 to 22)
    - Article on Antal Hidas's novel Gospodin Fitsek, undated, (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letters to Agnes Kun signed by Katia, 1963, 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Kopelev, Lev, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, [1957-1974], undated, (47 autograph letters signed, 2 typed letters signed, 12 autograph postcards signed, 1 telegram) (Box 1, Folder 25 to 27)
  - Kozlov Family, 1984, see Polevoi, Boris (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Levik, Vil'gel'm, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1960-1975, undated, (12 autograph letters signed, 5 autograph postcards signed, 2 telegrams) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Marmazhov, Il'ia, Antal Hidas, 1954-1970, undated, (4 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph postcard signed, 1 telegrams) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Marshak, Samuil, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Ialta, July 27, 1963, (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Martynov, Leonid and Nina (nee Popova), to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1951-1978, undated, (42 autograph letters signed, 17 autograph postcards signed) (Box 1, Folder 31 to 35)
  - Mil'chakov, Aleksandr, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, 1966-1969, (1 autograph letter signed, 4 autograph postcards signed) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Morits, Iunna, to Agnes Kun, Moscow, [1955], (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Orlova, Raisa Davydovna, see Kopelev, Lev
  - Otten, Petr:
    - To Antal Hidas, Omsk, 1961-1975, undated, (5 autograph letters signed, 17 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - To Eduard Otten from Antal Hidas, 1976, (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Papernyi, Zinovii and Valeriia, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, 1960-1976, undated (, 42 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph postcard signed, 3 telegrams) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 3)
  - Pervomaiskii, Leonid:
    - To Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Kiev, Irpen', 1948-1975, undated, (8 autograph letters signed, 18 typed letters signed, 2 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 4 to 5)
    - Hidas, A. to Leonid Pervomaiskii, undated, (2 drafts of a letter) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Polevoi, Boris, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1959-1984, undated, (44 autograph letters signed, 9 typed letters signed, 33 autograph postcards signed, 4 telegrams. ); There are also postcards from B. Polevoi's son Aleksei. (Box 2, Folder 6 to 10)
  - Prokof'ev, Aleksandr, to Antal Hidas, Leningrad, 1961, (1 typed letter signed, 1 telegram) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rozhdestvenskii, Robert, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, undated, (1 autograph letter signed) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rozov, Viktor, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1964-1968, (3 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Samoilov, David, to Agnes Kun, [1960s], (8 autograph letters signed, 5 typed letters signed) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stel'makh, Mykhailo, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, [1959]-1974, (2 autograph letters signed, 2 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Surkov, Aleksei, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1960-[1976], (7 autograph letters signed, 1 typed letter signed, 8 autograph postcards signed, 7 telegrams) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tikhonov, Nikolai, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas:
    - Original letters, 1954-1973, undated, (6 autograph letters signed, 1 autograph postcard signed) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Typed copies of letters, 1949-1976, (138 pages) (Box 2, Folder 18 to 20)
  - Treneva, Natal'ia, to Agnes Kun, 1959-1968, undated, (5 autograph letters signed, 4 telegrams) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Turkov, Andrei, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1964-1973, undated, (11 autograph letters signed, 4 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Venclova, Antanas, to Antal Hidas, 1953, 1963, (3 autograph letters signed) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Zabolotskii-Kaverin Family, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, 1973, undated, (2 autograph letters signed, 2 autograph postcards signed) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Zharov, Aleksandr, to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas, Moscow, December 31, 1959, (1 typed postcard signed) (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series II: Writings, 1940-1987, undated
  The series comprises mainly manuscripts of Antal Hidas and famous Russian poets. Organized in two Subseries.
  - Subseries II.1: Antal Hidas's Writings, 1943-1968, undated
    Contains typescript with holograph corrections of Hidas's memoirs. The memoirs are compilation of Hidas's essays written in various years. Arranged according to page numeration.
    - Memoirs, (carbon copy of typescript with holograph corrections)>
      - "Razgovor s samim soboi," undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - "Kak ia liubliu vas, rebiata! ," 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        (about A. Fadeev)
      - "Nedostaet odnogo cheloveka," 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        (about Bruno Jasienski)
      - "Samoe glavnoe," (about Gorkii), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - "Pered romanom," 1962 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - "Dorogie moi… khoroshie…," undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - "Pamflet i ego istoriia," 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - "Romanticheskii revoliutsioner," 1961-1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        (about Karikas)
      - "Na den' rozhdeniia," undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - "Byli i budut…," 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        (about I. Mikitenko)
      - "Avtoportret," 1943 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "Pobedil on - Miklosh Radnoti," undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - "Slovo k molodym," undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "My pered nim v dolgu," undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
        (about Maiakovskii)
      - "Mon Diue!" undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - 'Stroki, obletevshie mir," undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Oblaka: rech', proiznesennaia v Borzhomi na soveshchanii poetov za kruglym stolom," 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - "Razgovor s chepel'tsami," undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - "Dvorik ty moi dvorik: Bela Bartok v Moskve," undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "Seismograf i dvigatel' dushi," undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
        (about L. Martynov)
      - "Na strazhe dobra," undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "Moi otvet," undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - "Perelistaem zimu," undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - "Duet veterok s Dunaia," undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
        (about Mate Zalka)
      - "Miniatiury," undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - "Obeliski postaviat im," undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Subseries II.2: Writings by Others, 1940-1987, undated
    The Subseries contains mainly holograph manuscript and typescripts of original poetry and translations by famous Russian poets, such as Boris Pasternak, Nikolai Chukovskii, Mariia Petrovykh, Semen Kirsanov, Boris Slutskii, David Samoilov, Leonid Pervomaiskii, Leonid Martynov, Vsevolod Rozhdestvenskii, Andrei Voznesenskii, Nikolai Zabolotskii. Zabolotskii's writings include a bound typed manuscript "Stolbtsy i poemy. Stikhotvoreniia." N. Zabolotskii compiled this book of his poems in 1958 and considered it a complete edition of his poetry. This handmade book is one of seven copies. The Subseries also includes memoirs of Ivan Borisov and Ferenc Jancsik, and Semen Budennyi's essay on Bela Kun. There is also a photograph of Ivan Borisov, which remains with his memoirs, and three drawings of Leonid Martynov, which are stored along with his writings.
    - Akhmatova, Anna. "Requiem," undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
      (samizdat typescript received from A. Akhmatova)
    - Borisov, Ivan Kuz'mich. "Tragicheskaia ispoved' Litvinova Vladimira Pavlovicha - zhivshego s 1892 goda po 1950," 1964, (typescript with holograph corrections; Borisov's photograph, [1918]) (Box 3, Folder 28 to 32)
    - Budennyi, Semen. "Nash drug Bela Kun," undated, (signed typescript, 5 pages) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chukovskii, Nikolai. Translation of Sandor Petofi's poem, undated (, typescript with holograph corrections of Agnes Kun, 4 pages) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Inber, Vera. Translation of Endre Ady's poems, (holograph manuscript); see Series I: Correspondence--Inber (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Jancsik, Ferenc. "Ispoved' vengerskogo kommunista," 1987, (carbon copy of typescript, signed, 16 pages) (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Kedrin, Dmitrii. Translation of Sandor Petofi's poems, undated, (holograph manuscript, 32 pages) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Kirsanov, Semen. Original poem and translation, 1962, undated, (typescript with holograph corrections; original poem is signed; 5 pages) (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Knipovich, Evgeniia. Article on Antal Hidas's novel "Gospodin Fitsek", (typescript with holograph corrections); see Series I: Correspondence--Knipovich (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Kopelev, Lev:
      - "Berlin. Nachalo vesny shest'desiat chetvertogo goda," undated (, carbon copy of typescript with holograph corrections; 64 pages) (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Poeziia muzhestva i dobra," undated (, signed typescript with holograph corrections; 11 pages) (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "Sila i nezhnost'," undated, (typescript of synopsis of his book about Antal Hidas; 2 pages) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Larina, Anna (aka Larina-Bukharina). Transcript of Nikolai Bukharin's letter of 1937 "Budushchim pokoleniiam rukovoditelei partii" with her foreword, 1987, (holograph manuscript; 4 pages) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Levik, Vil'gel'm. Translation of Sandor Petofi's poem, undated, (typescript with holograph corrections; 1 page) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Martynov, Leonid:
      - Translations of Janos Arany's, Endre Ady's, Attila Jozsef's, and Antal Hidas's poems, and Mihaly Vorosmarty's drama, undated, (typescripts and holograph manuscripts) (Box 4, Folder 11 to 15)
      - Poemy. Moskva: Sovetskii pisatel', 1940 (Box 4, Folder 16)
        (book with Martynov's inscription to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas)
      - Various poetry and translations, see Series I: Correspondence--Martynov (Box 1, Folders 31-35)
      - Drawings, undated, (3 pencil drawings) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Pasternak, Boris. Translations from Hungarian, undated, (typescripts with holograph corrections; 53 pages) (Box 4, Folder 18 to 20)
    - Pervomaiskii, Leonid. Draft of poem, 1972, see Series I: Correspondence--Pervomaiskii (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Petrovykh, Mariia. Translations of Sandor Petofi's poems, undated, (signed typescripts with holograph corrections; 4 pages) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Rozhdestvenskii, Vsevolod. Translations of Sandor Petofi's poems, undated, (holograph manuscripts; 3 pages) (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Samoilov, David. "Detskii risunok," undated, (typescript of poem; 1 page) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Slutskii, Boris. Translations of Antal Hidas's poems; article about Endre Ady; original poetry, undated, (typescripts and holograph manuscripts; 11 pages) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Tikhonov, Nikolai. Translations of Sandor Petofi's and Antal Hidas's poems, undated, (signed typescripts with holograph corrections; 6 pages) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Voznesenskii, Andrei. Original poems, 1962, undated, (typescripts with holograph corrections; 21 pages) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Zabolotskii, Nikolai:
      - "Stirka bel'ia," undated, (holograph manuscript of poem; 1 page) (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "Stolbtsy i poemy. Stikhotvoreniia" (Box 5, Folder 8)
        (Bound typescript. This handmade book is one of seven copies. N. Zabolotskii compiled this book in 1958 and considered it as a complete edition of his poetry)
      - "Stonet Dunai." Translations of Antal Hidas's poems, 1946, (holograph manuscript; 15 pages) (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Series III: Printed Materials, 1917-1944, undated
  The Series includes are edition of Maiakovskii's Liubliu (which is claimed to be from Lili Brik's personal library; Martynov' Poemy with inscription to Agnes Kun and Antal Hidas; Communist and Soviet propaganda pamphlets, 1918-1944; and nine issues of the newspaper Edinstvo of 1917. The newspapers are stored in BAR Flat box #5. All items of this series are cataloged in CLIO.
  - Books:
    - Maiakovskii, Vladimir. Liubliu, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      (from Lili Brik's personal library)
    - Martynov, Leonid. Poemy. Moskva: Sovetskii pisatel', 1940, see Series II: Writings--Subseries II.2: Writings by Others--Martynov (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Communist and Soviet propaganda pamphlets, 1918-1944 (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
  - Periodicals:
    - Edinstvo: ezhednevnaia rabochaia gazeta, pod redaktsiei G.V. Plekhanova, 1917 (Box Flat Box #5)
      no.13, 16-18, 26, 29, 34, 44, 47
- Third Parties Materials, 1915-1947
  The Series comprises of personal documents (various IDs) of M. Martsinovich, E. Pokras, and A. Razorenova.
  - Personal Documents of: (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Martsinovich, Mariia, 1923-1942
    - Pokras, Evgeniia, 1929-1943
    - Razorenova, Aleksandra, 1915
    - Unidentified, 1947